A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice, Human Rights and Governance, Office Files of Sara Rios FA1443
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice, Human Rights and Governance, Office Files of Sara Rios
1993-2003
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rios, Sara E.
Ford Foundation
FA1443
1.3 Cubic Feet 4 boxes (3 letter document containers and 1 half letter document container)
Scope and Contents
The collection contains miscellaneous office files of Sara Rios, former Director of the Human Rights and Governance Unit within the Peace and Social Justice Division at the Ford Foundation. Her office files contain conference files, reports, press materials, correspondence, and publications.
Biographical / Historical
Sara Rios served as Director of the Human Rights and Governance Unit at the Ford Foundation from 2005-2012. Previously, she was the Program Officer for Racial Justice and Minority Rights from 2002-2005. Rios earned her Juris Doctor degree at the University of Toledo College of Law and was admitted to the Ohio Bar in 1986. Rios left the Ford Foundation in 2012 to become president of the Ruth Mott Foundation in Flint, Michigan. She passed away from ALS in 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2018 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2018:038.
Arrangement
Arranged as received from the Ford Foundation.
Ford Foundation; Human rights; Social justice
- The Civil Rights Project, Harvard University, 1998 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Roundtable Convening on Community-Based Leadership, April 23-24, 1998
- The Latino Civil Rights Crisis, The Civil Rights Project, 1997 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  A Symposium Co-sponsored by The Harvard Civil Rights Project at Harvard University and The Tomas Rivera Policy Institute
- A Review of the Ford Foundation's Work Related to Hispanics in the United States, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Uruguay Trip, 2003 May 5-10 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  Notebook - October 2002; correspondence (some in Spanish); Affirmative Action Affinity Group, Montevideo, Uruguay; Summary Outline of Brazilian Legal Issues Affecting Racial Discrimination, Shearman and Sterling (March 6, 2002); Memos; Discussion with Afro-Colombian Mayors (April 22, 2003); Overview of US Affirmative Action Programs and Litigation in the Higher Education Context, Robin A. Lenhardt; Afro-Descendants in Brazil and Uruguay; Affirmative Action Affinity Group; Medicine and the Racial Divide, Elizabeth Phimister; Program Officers' Memorandum Draft by Sara Rios; Disarming the Private Attorney General, Pamela Karlan; High School Graduation Rates in the US; Minority Rights Group newsletter
- US Court of Appeals 9th Circuit, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Two Towns of Jasper - Outreach Proposal, Presented by Two Tone Productions and Working Films, 2002 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Comision Colombiana de Juristas, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- CivilRights.org Press Printouts, 2002 November 6 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Funders' Collaborative Fund for Racial Justice Innovation, 2003 January 6 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- National Conference for Community and Justice, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Taking America's Pulse II - Executive Summary; Faith Leaders on Intergroup Relations: Perspectives and Challenges; Hate: A Concept Examined; Taking America's Pulse II: NCCJ's 2000 Suevey of Intergroup Relations in the United States; National Conference for Community and Justice proposal to the Ford Foundation
- Studies 2000: Discovering the Cultural Formations of Asian and Pacific Island Communities, Wildflowers Institute, 2000 July 23-25 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Center for Voting and Democracy, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Budget information; correspondence; New Electoral Systems for a Changing America, A Proposal to the Ford Foundation for General Support Prepared by Rob Richie, Executive Director, Center for Voting and Democracy (March 2002)
- Hispanic Civil Rights Series, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Arte Publico Press general info; Arte Publico Press, 2001 Complete Catalog; Hispanic Civil Rights Series general info
- Alan Jenkins Program Officer's Memo, 1998-2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Citizens' Commission for Civil Rights, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Grant No.: 098011622; grant document drafts; press materials; Rights at Risk: Equality at Risk: Equality in an Age of Terrorism (February 12, 2002)
- Resolutions on Education, 1970-1993: An Education Department Publication, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (Box 3, Folder 19)
- NAACP 1997 88th Annual Convention, Pittsburgh, PA - A Hearing: Does Racial Discrimination Exist in the US Military Justice System, Rachelle M. Jackson, RMR, 1997 July 17 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Field Guide to the Global Economy, Sarah Anderson and John Cavanagh with Thea Lee and the Institute for Policy Studies, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Justice for All?: A Report on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgendered Youth in the New York Juvenile Justice System, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Authors: Randi Feinstein, Andrea Greenblatt, Lauren Hass, Sally Kohn, Julianne Rana; An independent report commissioned by the Lesbian and Gay Youth Project of the Urban Justice Center
- From Poverty to Punishment: How Welfare Reform Punishes the Poor, Applied Research Center, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Local Government Guide to the Internet, Online Resources for Communities, Priscilla Salant and Christy Dearien, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- National Municipal Policy and Resolutions, National League of Cities, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Adopted at the 2001 Congress of Cities, Atlanta, Georgia, December 8, 2001
- 2002 Staff Directory, State Municipal Leagues, National League of Cities, 2002 April (Box 4, Folder 26)
- 2002 Directory of City Policy Officials and Resource Guide, Reflects November 2001 Elections, National League of Cities (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Internal: International Human Rights Training for Indigenous Peoples, A Review, Analysis, and Inventory of Programs, The Ford Foundation, 2002 May (Box 4, Folder 28)